hi it's February 8th 2023 we're in
meeting 15 of the octave textbook group
we're in our
second discussion in cohort 2 on chapter
six
so
last week we looked at a few
questions and
in this modeling
chapter
there's many
questions and topics we can come to so
does anybody want to just raise a
question or thought on six
otherwise we will look through questions
and see what we can do
yeah well I I've put a few questions
there that came to my mind
[Music]
great which one would you like to start
with
um so so we already talked about this
last time this figure 6.1
on page 110 I believe it is
and
now where is it
page 108.
and um
and my question was this vertical
connection there between active States
and sensory States and
um I was not able to really understand
why we would need to model this and I've
put this into the question there
um under chapter 6 when I read out that
question
so how is the mutual interaction between
active States and sensory States meant
can they mutually change their states
without impacting neither internal nor
external States so that means they cycle
around if yes what is supposed to what
is it to post model for instance
put their cycle around a thousand times
mutually modifying their states and then
eventually arrive at a state where they
change the external or internal States
somehow
so means my question is if they're
mutually
are able to change inside these Markov
blankets the states without any Trace in
the external or internal States then
they can cut a pulled or manipulate
themselves in to come into a situation
where suddenly they produce a Trace
and if this is allowed then I'm
wondering what
what are we supposed to Marble
with such processes
so
so because I mean you can then explain
any arbitrary Behavior
and is it is it curing complete this
kind of machine that we're then trying
to implement there
um and um and and and basically uh
and doesn't it undermine
explainability of behavior
so
I guess you got my
my question but maybe I'm understanding
something wrong there
anyone else want to give yes please
Ollie and then go on
I believe those bi-directional paths
between active States and sensory states
are uh simply there for the model to be
more comprehensive and
they basically refers to they basically
refer to something like reflex arcs
which don't necessarily need to pass
through cortical paths
so that's something much more directly
manipulated
but of course those
direct paths between active States and
sensory States could be removed from the
diagram and we we can talk about
bypassing internal Estates or external
States when the reflex are happen but I
believe
those direct paths are there to account
for those kinds of
um intrinsic or some somehow those
um
the behaviors akin to reflex arcs
thanks Ali but but isn't this isn't this
then uh the
question of what you define to be
internal States if you say the entire
states only start
up from a certain point above the spine
at below it's no more internal then it's
an arbitrary decision right so you could
just also say that everything that
happens in the hippothalamus is not part
of internal States and only what is in
the prefrontal cortexes and I mean how
um
I'm I mean this is arbitrary you know
and if what is the reason to have such
kind of arbitrary decisions there
you could then put everything
into into this direct interaction or
depending on where your
yeah Yes actually it is to some degree
an arbitrary boundary because uh as we
also read in chapter six defining the
mark of blanket boundary that depends on
the situation we're trying to model so
it's not necessarily something
predefined and it depends what Behavior
we're trying to model so uh yeah in
sense in some sense it depends on the
context
and yeah
but but see my point is if we are trying
to model reflexes we would put this into
the internal States
but if we are not trying to uh I mean I
mean if you allow this direct
interaction between active States and
sensory States
you're basically
isn't isn't this just like saying there
is behavior that we cannot explain but
we want to have it in our model
I will give a thought but first Jacob
yeah I was
um
I just wanted to add that
you could I I think I agree with Ali's
point that it's probably there for
um more I guess
explainability or
just to kind of
um
owing to the fact that the active States
and sensory states form like a single
blank uh blanket but I think you could
also think of it as enabling another
loop with the internal States perhaps
where if the external states are very
high dimensional and you're in a
partially observable state where you
have like a window of observation then
the active states can directly change
the sensory states without necessarily
changing the external States it's like
um psychotic eye movement it's not
changing the external States but it is
changing your window of observation
through action and I think that
um
Carl mentioned in one of his talks that
these arrows might also represent
different levels of sophistication but
I'm not totally
clear on
um on how that uh can be explained
thanks okay a few
um angles on this so I think the general
uh modeler
perspective is what some call an
arbitrary decision others might call a
model or degree of freedom so the idea
that just because something is
subjective or arbitrary devalues it
rather that is the space in which
decisions are made and so it's rarely a
bad thing
to have a broader family to choose from
and then
um let's imagine that there is oh that
okay second point is the particular
partition
which is this one so here's the particle
the blanket and the internal States
and then the autonomous states which are
the ones that were most interested in
developing imperatives for
are internal States and active States so
those are called the autonomous States
they're the ones like if you had total
control of your mind and action and you
had the optimal policy like you'd be
thinking and acting optimally
and then that leaves the sensory States
as being what we're trying to reduce the
Divergence with in terms of what we have
actually observed and what we expect
slash prefer okay so the particular
partitioning
comes into being
or a defined set of variables in a Bayes
graph
it's not like one variable is simply
internal States
so depending on what model you construct
there might be a variable might be
internal with respect to one but then
blanket with respect to another
so if we were doing an isocating model
like you you might be able to make a
base graph
where different things corresponded to
differences
um and then also
this allows us to have a model
where the entire cognitive behavior
is accomplished by the blanket
so you could have a model where these
edges with internal states do nothing
and that is corresponding to the the
strange types
that we talked about previously like it
corresponds to an inert particle that's
not doing anything that we might call
truly cognitive which is to say that
it's perception and action are mediated
entirely by its blanket
and so there are systems where the
entire performance
can be understood on the holograph
on the blanket
other systems
we might want to extend that
and there might be a system where this
Edge is parameterized from empirical
data to be zero or where you set this to
be zero
but another way to view this
um graph
is as a four by four Matrix
where the edges reflect relationships
so if it was just four independent
variables it would look like the
identity Matrix
and then the off diagonal elements of
that four by four Matrix
reflect the causal influence of
different variables on each other
and so you can have the Around the Clock
you could have the bi-directional Around
the Clock
you could have the the telepathic model
where there's a direct Edge between
internal and external
so
you could fit the full 4x4
but that would be equivalent to fitting
a linear regression with four variables
testing for all by all interactions
which you might want to do also that has
the least statistical power and so in
terms of which edges it makes sense to
to fix to zero removing the telepathy
slash telekinesis Edge
is a really important one
and then there's a few other edges that
are removed like internal backward
causing sense and external backwards
causing action
but that's not to say this is the only
topology of the oxygen perception Loop
Michael
yeah so I'm just wondering how well I I
said as I said no I'm trying I'm I'm
trying to apply this to our translation
process data so we have gaze data and
keystrokes and so on and there is one
observation in a translation that
the it's a mixture of of priming
processes sort of a partially
automatized processes and monitoring
processes where higher cognitive
decisions or reflective thought maybe
comes into play so it means that the
translation is a mixture of automatized
trans production routines and monitoring
intervention and I'm wondering whether
this model then word
um
could be used to say that these priming
processes are the direct links between
sensation and action
um and um and and this higher order
reflective processes and so somebody
maybe thinks of and which context
does the translation make sense and all
this whether this would then be better
modeled with the other route so
um
so in this case of course these priming
processes happen in the head somewhere
it's not in the spine right so
translator produces nevertheless uses
the head but there's priming processes
and other kinds of processes do you
think that makes sense to view it that
way
I think we can actually very quickly
run the recipe and understand
Ali first and then we'll come to the
recipe
um I think the one point that might help
to understand this diagram slightly
better is that uh in most uh most of the
literature related to active inference
nfep the word particle is used to refer
to the Joint set of internal States and
blanket States but in some other papers
instead of particles they use system or
agent so uh actually in some sense those
markup blankets uh belong to the to the
agent we're trying to model uh but
the reason
or behind distinguishing between the
markup blanket and internal state is
purely for modeling purposes
uh I'm not sure if it makes sense uh or
not but yeah so in any case those markup
blankets
would actually constitute parts of this
ancient agent were trying to model here
okay thank you let's just imagine just
rapid fire you have the most translation
um experience but others can like
imagine
um potentially what
a translation setting would be
so we'll just give one thought we don't
need to expound on all of them but we're
gonna focus on
the particular partition and then we'll
use that to understand like what family
of action perception Loops are we
actually fitting so
what question are we looking to answer
or what phenomena are we looking to
model
are you asking me sure what's an
interesting question for you or for
anyone about translation human
translation
yeah so we would like I guess try to
understand
translator environment interaction and
how translators
produce translations
what are the difficulties what are the
processes that goes on go on
difficulties
okay
which data do we have
we have the observations on the Markov
blankets so we have case data
reading patterns on the source and the
target text and we have typing Behavior
so the insertions and deletions
that happen in the texts
okay
all right
so
now we're going to go to the form of the
generative model as we mentioned last
week like it doesn't have to necessarily
be in this order each time
but
now we're going to hear no
Markov blankets need to be mentioned
this is just empirically which data
exists or what are we trying to model
now let's think about
um
using the ontology what are the
particular partitions going to be
so
okay
the action States
these ones do correspond to actions that
you you have collected on
so we have isocades
which there's actually there are active
models of sentence comprehension
and type A
so here the isocades could be understood
as being selected from directions
that the eye can move and the typing
could be understood as like at the
letter or the word scale
okay what sense data
or sense states are going to be incoming
well I would I would I would put this
eye circuits into the sense
thing or the reading pattern so with an
eye tracker we can see
where the eyes are on the text so we can
see the the items the tokens that are
read so yes so the stents say could be
the incoming visual perception which
token is um being viewed
but the the isocate is an action
yeah but okay this is a policy up down
left right that the eye can move to
obtain a different sense state
okay so
they're describing random variables in a
base graph they're not necessarily
describing
um spatially separated parts of an
organism
okay now this is where there's a lot of
degrees of freedom in what is being
modeled as the internal the external
state so does anyone have a thought on
what the internal or the external States
might be
so the way we we are trying to see this
is that the internal States
can be fluent so the the person can be
in a steady state so they can be just
looking a little bit head fluently
translating so it's a kind of uh
fluent production state
exactly non-equilibrium steady state or
there can be in a state where they are
confused or hesitating we can see this
by the eye gaze data going back and
forth and the text
revision trying out some options and so
on so that's kind of a hesitation that's
what in internal state in my
understanding searching and well a kind
of surprise
uh
or they could be in a state where they
try to so what I think it's called um
epistemic
State whether or where they go ahead
intentionally and try to you know
activate the
correct or the appropriate mental
resources to be able to then use this in
in a translation phase in a steady state
does that make sense
okay
I I might put forth that fluency
confusion hesitation or just thinking
these are like categorizations
that you're going to be able to
delineate from the phase space of a
variable and so the question is what is
the variable
so one option but anyone feel free to
give a different option would be the
external state are the true hidden
semantics of the text
and the internal state would be the
received semantics of the text
like just thinking about
um numbers like we're or you know we're
we're doing a cooking recipe
but we're less fluent or We're
translating a cooking recipe
so it's three cups of sugar and two cups
of flour
we're going to be
engaging in isocades
to reduce our uncertainty about the
semantics of a text
but of course we can't directly see the
semantics of a text what do we get
incoming visual tokens
what do visual tokens do
visual tokens reduce our uncertainty
about the semantics what do we do now
that we've resolved semantics well we
can take actions
which constraining or if we didn't have
to type this is a complex because
there's like two kind of very different
kinds of actions but let's just say we
were just reading to understand so we're
doing silence translation we're just
reading and understanding something in a
in a language
so then
if you had sufficiently resolved your
uncertainty
about us about the the word
you'd imagine that you would take an
isocade
to where you expect the next piece of
semantics to be resolved
next word
whereas if the incoming sensory States
are not adequately resolving your
uncertainty
you might pause or you might even go
back
and then from these from patterns of
flow across the the the agent States
then you could categorize those into
categories like fluent reading hesitant
reading
distracted
that's one option or
one can imbue the model with like a
little bit more like a more opinionated
model
where you could say an internal state is
going to be
whether they're in this or that
mode
so just to kind of summarize that
you can have internal States
reflect
semantics
and then have a secondary categorization
of different zones in that phase space
or you can have a more opinionated model
that is explicitly
modeling transitions between for example
fluent production and confusion
I need to think about this our good
ideas thank you yes yeah and then just
just to kind of let's just continue just
briefly to these last piece
um how would we set up the generative
model
well let's look at how they talk about
setting up the generative model
what are the variables and priors okay
so here was just natural language
so the semantics of a text so what
should that variable be are we reading a
text that's just ones and zeros
or is it is there going to be are we
doing genre detection and there's five
genre
or what is the actual State space
of different variables
again for typing are we going to have
the state space be letters
and then basically have like a
transition Matrix of letters
which is like some of the earliest
information Theory or will we have a
transition Matrix of words
or a transition Matrix of motifs
so those are all what some might call
subjective but they're modler degrees of
freedom there isn't the right answer
there's just what model is made we we
have actually something we call
activity units so we have we can chop up
the text into all the translation
process into smaller pieces where we can
see whether a person types or reads a
text or has concurrent typing and
reading and so we can chop up the
timeline into smaller units which we
call activity units and
um and then and this I think would be
the units on which we would like to um
work where so the idea here is not to
simulate a translation system we're
we're not so much interested what is
actually the text the translation being
produced but or say the textual elements
but rather the process elements so means
how long does it take what is the
interval between successive keystrokes
and what is the
um of what is the offset between gaze
and typing
typing and so on what are the gazing
patterns so how how long ahead do people
read in the text and so on so so it's
more the temporal structure that we want
to model not the
um
not the semantic structure actually
yes great
so we are not trying to simulate a
machine translation system
yep so this all right so this could be
simply
like the most coarse grained typing
model would be there's two affordances
typing or not typing
yes yeah and and again
one person could say these are
subjective differences between models
but these are the kinds of models if one
were to really do a research project on
that you could compare these three
models or you could say we chose to
pursue a model with this state space
for this reason or like which parts are
fixed and which must be learned well
we know that there's things that can be
learned by real humans but the question
is what is going to be fixed or learned
in this model
and fixed
models are simpler computationally
and they have a simpler interpretation
but sometimes the function of learning
then gets displaced and results in
distorted behavior from other parameters
so this is why modeling is an iterative
process and why it involves constructing
sometimes vast families of cousin models
to understand the stability of different
parameters
because maybe once you're you enable
learning on something
then that might change another parameter
because all of a sudden it doesn't need
to be taking on some kind of role
um
and then
uh
which aspects are perception like
which aspects are learning like
and then the last question is like how
to set up the generative process
interesting little hidden character
what are the elements
not sure if that's just my reader but
that's very interesting
what are the elements of a generative
process and how do they differ from a
generative model so the generative
process the niche it could be another
Octave of agent or it could just be
a static text
that passes tokens in order
or it could be a conversant
but the exact structure
of the state space
and then which families of statistical
distributions one chooses for priors
those are modular degrees of freedom
there won't just be one for any natural
system
in in our last third what would be
another good chapter six direction to go
thank you
there's a lot
foreign
the decision
the choice between discrete and
continuous models is more simply
articulated using discrete time models
okay who has a thought on why that is
that's a very good question
here's one possible answer
um again
um why is it
the decision to model alternative
futures
contingent on policy selection is
largely tied up with the choice between
discrete and continuous models
why are alternative futures more simply
articulated with discrete time models
in the discrete State space model
figure 4.3 as usual
hidden States
past
now future and I could have temporal
depth even further
but we're making an explicit prediction
about like
the hidden State at time seven
if we're interested in time depth of
seven
and then if we have a four two
affordances
we're evaluating all of those
combinatorics
every
policy which is a sequence of actions of
length seven for each of those policies
we're going to evaluate what the hidden
States will be
so you could ask under policy 22
up up down up up
what would the hidden State be and then
What observations might I expect
so the discrete State space
formulization
is amenable to talking about specific
moments in specific policy
that are under consideration
and then of course like those policies
are going to be evaluated
according to
their expected free energy
The Continuous time case
is structurally similar which is the big
visual message of figure 4.3
but note that while B in the discrete
time case
is a transition Matrix how does the time
Point move into the next time point so
you multiply forward with b and then
that's how the hidden States move
forward
and that's where policy intervenes how
hidden States change Through Time
in the continuous time case it's a lot
more like a Taylor series expansion
because node 3 here
is the derivative of x
conditioned upon X and V causes
and so in this case it's not that we're
explicitly predicting
at
five time Steps From the future if I do
this or that
but rather under a given policy that's
being considered
there's a function that's being
approximated with higher and higher
derivatives
so it doesn't have as straightforward
of an interpretation
you still could ask
under this Taylor series approximation
at five time steps out what's my
prediction so you can ask that
and you could even compare under
um derivative
uh
under V 1 or V2
two different ways of taking derivatives
we can evaluate so it's not that you
can't evaluate
the um
alternate Futures contingent on policy
selection
and that is exactly what happens with
expected free energy in continuous State
space models so it is possible to
compare alternate Futures and still use
expected free energy
but
only in the discrete case do we actually
have sequences of actions defined along
the way
so so does this mean if in the
non-discrete case
we need to look into the seventh
derivation to see what happens say seven
points in time ahead
no in there's a great question
um you could do
um you could do a Taylor series uh a
depth of one
so a Taylor series depth of uh with
approximation of one
see if there's a graph okay
okay
so let's just say we do a Taylor series
with one term
so it just is literally a flat line
we can look ahead any depth
we could look ahead a thousand time
points with a Taylor series depth of one
and we don't need to explicitly predict
those thousand time steps whereas if we
wanted a thousand time steps deep with
discrete
we would need to explicitly model every
single step what is the B Matrix from
997 to 998
so that's the strength and the weakness
of the Taylor series The Taylor series
you can have
a really simple
um approximation oh well how about two
terms let's do the green one
and you could use that two-term
approximation
any depth
and as you get
um more and more terms
they
just like principal component Dimensions
they always they always make a better
and better approximation
sometimes a lot sometimes a little but
you always do get better so kind of like
the contact zone between the true
function blue cosine in this situation
the contact Zone
as you do higher approximations always
extends out more
like
Brown peels off here purple peels off
here
and that's part of the issue is also a
Taylor series and just modeling General
you don't really know how well you're
doing
because the um the green line is not
going to complain oh what's the what's
the cosine approximation of 11 that's
negative 200.
no
but the model is not going to complain
Ali
possible unmute Ali
thank you
uh first of all sorry I have some
connection problems I'm not sure if my
voice is intelligible but uh one
interesting point is uh actually some
neuroscientists such as
rich solati and senegalia into prominent
Italian neuroscientists explained this
choice of actions in terms of Mosaic of
zones so each Zone in this Mosaic would
contain information about the parameters
that must be used to select the most
appropriate variant of action to act on
an object or
okay
okay we we did just lose
um a little bit we got that part
Mosaic of zones
um
okay let's see if we can get but um so
suffice to say discrete State space
downside
you have to explicitly model
you know the upside you get to
explicitly model downside you have to
explicitly model
so if you want to do temporal depth of
30 you need to run that out
across the combinatorics of policy
for a depth of 30. so the computational
complexity can be extremely high which
we explored in the branching time active
inference discussions
so here is like it makes a massive tree
search
so it's kind of like a chess algorithm
at least some chess algorithms
continuous State space
has a very very defined
computational complexity
however
it doesn't have the exact
um
ability to say like other than just
generating this smooth function you
can't really say too much more
like how would it have been different if
I went up up up up up down versus up
again
okay
we
um
Ollie we we heard you were the Mosaic of
zones so you could maybe
um add the links into the page
any one or two more questions that
people would like to come to
how about this one
what is meant by variable States or
observations how can States be
continuous
so States can be continuous
a continuous variable is like one where
there's a smooth knob
that is controlling the value so it's
like a this is like a smooth knob
could be any number between zero and one
it could be 0.7772
or discrete could be like zero or one
or it could be one two three four five
so that's how States can be continuous
um what is meant by variable
States or observations
so variables and states
basically mean the same thing
like a variable is just a it's a
parameter
in an equation or in a program
and variables take on States
so the variable could be continuous
between zero and one and then the state
that it's in is 0.6
and then observations
are one kind of variable
Michael
yeah so so how about you then model the
difference between the observations and
the states is is there a problem is that
straightforward
um so so if if I had have a knob and I
can turn it on and off so I have two
observations for that knob or I can turn
it you know like a demo or something
with infinite number of observations but
the knob itself
is just one thing so I'm not sure yeah
great I should understand that
okay so we're we're doing a volume knob
the nav is the territory it has like
physical you know it's made of metal
okay now there's multiple maps that you
could make of that knob
you could ask whether it's playing or
not
that would be a binary discrete space
you could say we're gonna do
um 10
volume levels
this would be discrete
with 10 possible States
or you could do a hundred
or you could do a continuous variable
any number from
zero to one
so it's like a it's a total classic map
territory question
State spaces
are about variables
variables are in the map
if I make a variable corresponding to
weight
like if a person
it could be over under a hundred pounds
it could be integers
it could be
tenths of a pound that's still a
discrete State space
it could be a continuous
number
um
Jonathan wrote you could then imagine
that observations could be discreet even
when States may be continuous it may be
that we can't tell the difference
between the very finely graded States
yes
great Point like just noticeable
difference
um and
when you do discretized models
it becomes like a trade-off where the
more coarse graining you do
the simpler the model is but you're
making bigger and bigger buckets that
are clumping together more and more
disparate things
whereas if you do this really fine scale
discretized model like hundredth of a
pound and we're going to be weighing
people
then you can get all these like bizarre
phenomena
where it's like well if they're 137.1
pound then this is the case but if
they're 137.2 then this is the case so
finding that optimal discretization
is a big Topic in optimization in
general and in modeling
um and then another piece to remember
the state space of the external state so
we're still not even talking about the
territory itself but the state space of
the external variables
so our
model of temperature
it doesn't have to be the same as the
cognitive model of the agents
so we could say
um in the simulation temperature is an
integer
and then they're going to have three
states cold just right and hot
or here in the external World it could
be continuous variable
and then in the brain it could be three
state or it could be a continuous
variable or it could be anything else
what matters is the observation coming
in
and then how that gets fit into the
generative model Ali
yeah apologies I got disconnected uh as
I was saying some neuroscientists
explain the choice of appropriate action
in terms of the Mosaic of zones uh and
by that they mean that each zone is the
Mosaic that would contain uh the the
information
to act upon the affordances or the
goal-directed sequences to act upon the
affordances so as an example uh take for
instance the task of picking up a cup of
coffee uh this seemingly simple task can
be done in various ways depending on
whether we are drinking from it in that
case which we would probably grasp it by
the handle
or if we're washing it so in that case
we would probably be grasp it by the rim
or moving it out of the way uh which
would which in that case the grass can
get by the body would probably be the
more appropriate sequence of action so
which of these actions is deemed
appropriate for a task
is worked out within that Mosaic of
zones which they also
correlates with some cortical areas
which
Maps those
Mosaic zones quite literally in order to
afford the agent
this ability to pick the appropriate
action in each situation
thank you cool
all right
that is our second discussion on chapter
six so six
in summary
outline some of the most important
design choices that have been made in
setting up an active inference model
we have explored a lot of
auxiliary routes and questions
and hopefully this conveys some of the
richness and excitement and openness
around making a model
because even for simple phenomena
there's many ways to do it and even for
simple phenomena it's not just about
making one model and parameterizing it
once it's like an iterated modeling
process where you're generating these
families of models
they provided a recipe some guidelines
and thoughts they point out that it
doesn't have to be followed in that
particular order
this sets up the remainder of the book
which puts the ideas into practice
through a series of illustrative
examples designed to showcase the
theoretical principles presented in the
first half of the book
in everything that follows the only
differences amongst the example rest on
the design choices we have highlighted
part two illustrates systems with
different boundaries
discrete or continuous Dynamics at
different time scales
and that will all be implementing active
so we're going to head into
chapter 7 next time
chapter 7 is active inference in
discrete time
we're going to look at generative models
that have a discrete time characteristic
chapter 8 is continuous time
so that distinction was kind of raised
earlier in figure 4.3 chapter 7 and 8
are like a pair that are going to
highlight those two different
possibilities chapter 9 is about data
driven analysis and chapter 10 as a
conclusion chapter so
that concludes this session
thanks everybody for the uh great times
and we'll come back next week for
chapter seven thank you
thank you